Guide to the Office of Admissions, School of Medicine, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Office of Admissions, School of Medicine, Yale University, records
1915-2005
RU 1005
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.75
The records consist of subject files, reports, policies, statistical composites, printed material, photographs, and studies of the Admissions Office of the Yale School of Medicine.
Yale University. School of Medicine
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 27-E (YRG 27-E), Records of departments, offices, programs, and projects of the Yale School of Medicine.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records were transferred from the Yale School of Medicine Office of Admissions, 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the materials is restricted. See Collection Contents for details.
Arrangement
The records are arranged alphabetically by topic.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of subject files, reports, policies, statistical composites, printed material, photographs, and studies of the Admissions Office of the Yale School of Medicine.
Medical colleges -- Admission; Yale University -- Admission; Yale University. School of Medicine -- Students; Yale University. School of Medicine
- Administrative and statistical records, 1915-2005; Accession 2006-A-207
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted until Jan 1, 2040
  - AAMC Association of American Medical Colleges
    - Data Book, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Trends in Medical Applicants and Matriculants, 1980-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Admissions Committee
    - Training Exercise, 1991, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Committee on Student Affairs, 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - First Meeting, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letters used in the Admissions Process, 1958-2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Memoranda to the Admissions Committee, 1957-2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Chairs
  - Admissions Office
    - Information on the operation of the Admissions Office, 1974-2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Admission Process Study by Gerard N. Burrow, William Kessen, Robert M. Milstein and Leland Wilkinson, 1972-1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Admissions Staff, 1985-2005 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Education and Student Affairs Personnel Photograph, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Information on individual staff members (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Job descriptions (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Staff positions (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Application forms, 1974-2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Alumni/Alumnae
    - Alumni Reunion Weekend, Association of Yale Alumni in Medicine, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Class Directory of Living Alumni, Yale School of Medicine, 1892-1967, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Report of the Yale Medical School class of 1964 to visit the medical school, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Student Affairs, Admissions, Financial Aid, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - AMCAS, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Articles on Yale Medical School Admissions and Education
    - Lentz, T. L. "Preparing for medical school." In Donaldson, R. M., Jr., K. S. Lundgren, and H. M. Spiro, eds., The Yale Guide to Careers in Medicine and the Health Professions: Pathways to Medicine in the 21st Century. Yale Univ. Press, New Haven, pp 43-48., 2003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Lippard, V. W. "The program of medical education at Yale." Connecticut Medicine, 24: 567., 1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Milstein, R. M., G. N. Burrow, L. Wilkinson, and W. Kessen. "Prediction of screening decisions in a medical school admissions process." Journal of Medical Education, 51: 626-633., 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - The Yale Program of Medical Education, 1966 September (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Time Magazine, "Unexpected dip. Fewer apply to medical school." p66., 1978 July 10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Viseltear, A. J. "333 Cedar Street: An oral history. A chapter in the history of contemporary medicine." Yale Journal of Biological Medicine, 58:29-49., 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Viseltear, A. J. "The Yale Plan of Medical Education: The early years." Yale Journal of Biological Medicine, 59:627-648. Signed, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Yale Medicine. Fall. "Admissions: how do you choose 103 students from 2886 applicants?" Thomas L. Lentz, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Yale Medicine. Fall. "Nothing Will Change in the School of Medicine's Admissions Policies." Thomas L. Lentz, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Yale Medicine. Winter/Spring. Office of Student Affairs., 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Yale Medicine. Summer. "With an interest in the past, admissions dean doubles as a chronicler of local lore.", 2005 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Books and Manuscripts on Yale Medical School Admissions and Education
    - Field, W. W. The Good Doctor Smith: Life and Times of Dr. Nathan Smith, 1762-1829. The Advocate Press, New Haven, 156pp. Field was a member of the Admissions Committee., 1992 (Box 1, Folder 11 - 15)
    - Lerner, Marguerite Rush. Medical School: The Interview and the Applicant. Barron's Educational Series, Inc., Woodbury, New York, 160pp., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Levitin, Howard. Pre-Med Handbook. Warner Books, New York, 322pp., 1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Thoms, H. ed. History of the Yale University School of Medicine, manuscript copy., circa 1955 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Education
    - An Academic Plan for the Yale University School of Medicine, Dean Leon E. Rosenberg, 1990 November (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Educational Concerns, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Integrated and Responsive Curriculum, 1991 September 21 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Memorandum on commentaries, 1991 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Masters in Health Sciences Research (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Mission and Educational Objectives, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Modified examination system, 1986 June 4 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Objectives of the Yale University School of Medicine, 1992 August 18 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Renewing the Yale System of Medical Education: Report of the Dean's Committee on Medical Education, 1999 September (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Report of the Task Force for Curriculum Evaluation, 1988 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Revision of the curriculum, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - The Yale Medical School Curriculum, S. C. Edberg, 1992 September 18 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Yale University School of Medicine. M.D. Curriculum, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Response to MD/PhD Program Suggestions, 2003 November 17 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Proposal to Accommodate Educational Needs of MD/PhD and Science Oriented Students in the Curriculum, 2004 March 24 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Financial Aid, 1920-2005 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Budgets, 1980-2005 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Financial Aid Packet, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Frequently Asked Questions about Financial Aid, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Statistics on loans and scholarships, 1920-1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Student Budget and Financial Planning, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Interview Book
    - Information booklet given to interviewees, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Legal
    - Office for Civil Rights, 1978, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - MD/PhD Program
    - Student Roster, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Graduates of M.S.T.P. Program, 1973-1984 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Program Handbook, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Trainees and Graduates, 1983-2005 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Medical Scientist Training Program, Yale University, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Yale School of Medicine, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Yale University. Medical Scientist Training Program, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Admissions Data, 2000-2005 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Program Presentation, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Medical College Admissions Test, 1985-2005 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Medical School Council, 1990-2005 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Memoranda
    - Memorandum to Dean, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Registration and Orientation Information, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Memos to Admissions Committee, 1968-1997 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1961-2006 (Box 2, Folder 24 - 45)
  - Minority Affairs, 1968-1997
    - Minority Recruitment Day (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Policies (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Statistics (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Daniels, Daryl K. African Americans at the Yale University School of Medicine. MD Thesis, 145pp., 1991 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Miscellaneous
    - YMS Strengths and Weaknesses, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Administrative Retreat, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Newspaper Articles
    - Miscellaneous articles, 1970-2001 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Originals faded originals, have been copied on acid-free paper, 1962-1989 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Policies
    - Admissions Policies, 1997-2004 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Other policies, 1978, 1987, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Policy on Certain Nonacademic Considerations in Medical School Admissions Process Technical Standards, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Policies and Procedures Book
  - Publications
    - Women in Medicine pamphlet, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Yale University School of Medicine. A Different Perspective, Office of Minority Affairs pamphlet, 1985, 1990, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Yale University School of Medicine. Admissions Overview booklet, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Yale University School of Medicine. An Introduction The Viewbook, 1997, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Reports
    - Admission Interview, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Medical Student Research, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Report on the Medical Scientist Training Program, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Report to Chairs Luncheon, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Report to Medical School Council on Admissions, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Research and Independent Study, Class entering, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Student Affairs, Admissions, Financial Aid, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - The Admissions Process at Yale University School of Medicine, Thomas L. Lentz, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Report on Admissions Season, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Second Look Weekend
    - Programs, 1990-2006 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Second Look Showcase videorecording, 2005; 6 computer files (DVD-Video)
      - Use copy, 1 optical disk (DVD) (Box 3.1U)
  - Statistics of Class Entering, 1992-2005 (Box 3, Folder 55 - 68)
  - Statistics - General
    - Calendar, 1915-1970 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Colleges of Applicants and Accepted Students, 1949-1962 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Miscellaneous Old Statistics, 1926-1985 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Old Statistics copies on acid free paper, 1920-1950 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Statistics, Graphs, 1967-2005 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Withdrawals and places offered, 1955-1970 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Women, 1916-1975 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Statistics Summary, 1977-2003 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Students
    - Concerns regarding the current environment as YSM and suggestions for improvement, Nancy Angoff, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Medical Student Handbook, 2000, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Memorial Service for Paul Powei Hung, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - MOOT. Medical School Outdoor Orientation Trip, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Student Enrollment by year of graduation, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - The Kit, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - White Jacket Coat Ceremony Programs, 1994-2005 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Studies
    - Study of Admissions Data on Students Experiencing Difficulty in Medical School, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Studies of students failing National Boards, Part I classes entering, 1988-1997 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Studies of students failing National Boards, Part I classes entering, 1971-1976 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Study of applicants with the PhD degree, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Talks on Admissions, 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Medical School Admissions. Trends, Procedures and Preparation. Harvard College Premedical Presentation, Thomas L. Lentz, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Second Look Weekend, Thomas L. Lentz, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Talk given to premedical students, Thomas L. Lentz, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Thirteen School Consortium, Shared Admissions Data, 1974-2005 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Women
    - Baserga, Susan J. "Louise Farnam and Her Colleagues. First Women Graduates of the Yale School of Medicine", 1987 (Box 3, Folder 77 - 78)
    - Statistics on Women at YSM (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Policies and Procedures Book
  - Statistics of Class Entering, 1927-1948 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Statistics of Class Entering, 1949-1991 (Box 5, Folder 80 - 122)
  - Composite Class Photographs
  - Classes of 1968-2005, 2008-2009 (Box 6, Folder 123)
  - 24/7 Medicine at Yale viewbook, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 124)